A Guide to the Papers of Imamu Amiri Baraka, 1960-1963
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Imamu Amiri Baraka, 1960-1963
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
7884
This collection consists of 27 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased by the Library on March 30, 1965.
Scope and Content Information
The papers consist of letters and postcards to Diane Di Prima. As joint editor, with Di Prima, of the poetry magazine Floating Bear, Baraka suggests material for the magazine, forwards new subscriber information, and asks that certain new magazines be noted in "Floating Bear."
Baraka mentions his own work, assesses some of his poems, and notes "Eyes in the Back of our Heads" by Denise Levertov, "Man Condemned to Death" by Jean Genet, and "Cain's Book" by Alex Trocchi. He writes of teaching at the New School for Social Research, contracting hepatitis from dirty needles, and being locked up at Bellevue. He mentions his parents, his family, Larry Wallrich, Alfred Leslie, Louis Ginsberg, Allen Ginsberg, Jack Kerouac and many of the Floating Bear contributors.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- LeRoi Jones to Diane Di Prima 1960 Jun 2, APCS, 1 p.
  "Ordered 5 texts from Larry Wallrich." Mentions Alfred Leslie in connection with "H.P." and "JUNGLE;" (Paul) Blackburn, (William) McNaughton. Asks if "4 Young Lady Poets" would interfere with her other books.
- L.J to D.D. 1961 Jan 5, APCS, 1 p.
  Asks Di Prima to review Eyes in the Back of Our Heads by Denise Levertov, and asks who should review Cain's Book by Alex Trocchi.
- L.J to D.D. 1961 Feb 5, APCS, 1 p.
  Gives new address for "AB" (Spellman?), adds Bob Kaufman's name and address to mailing list, asks that another copy be sent to Ellie.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Feb 11, APCS, 1 p.
  "Carl Soloman/ Pilgram State Hospital/ Brentwood, L.I."
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Mar 7, APCS, 1 p.
  Mentions several subscribers, asks if there is room on the back page of Floating Bear for a listing of quarterlies and books of note recieved recently.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Mar 11, ALS, 1 p. w/env.
  "More so-called statements. I guess we can stick 'em in here & there (?) / Amor,/ Tio Roi"
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Mar 14, APCS, 1 p.
  Gives name and address of a subscriber, suggests he be added to list only if "he sends you some loot."
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Apr 19, ALS, 1 p. w/env. inscribed with another subscriber's name and address
  Sends "some of Ron's poems--maybe for use in some future Bear" (Ron Loewinsohn). Mentions poems by Joel (Oppenheimer), (Bill) Berkson, (Charles) Olson, (Philip) Whalen, (Bruce) Boyd, (Stephen) Jonas, (Stuart) Perkoff for future issues. Gives names and address for two new magazines ( Crucible and Outburst) to be mentioned in Floating Bear.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 May 3, APCS, 1 p.
  Gives names and addresses of two new magazines to be mentioned: Evidence, which wants submissions, and Outcry.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Jun 5, ALS, 1 p. w/env
  Mentions several subscriptions. Suggests (John) Wieners, (Denise) Levertov, "guy from North Carolina" (Minor Davis?) for next issue.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Sep 6, TPC, 1 p.
  Name and North Carolina address of Minor Davis.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Oct 9, APCS, 1 p.
  Name and address of a subscriber.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Oct 22, APCS, 1 p.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Nov 2, ALS, 2 p. on 2 l. w/env.
  Sends three subscribers' names, asks if (Ron) Loewinsohn is on mailing list, encloses letter from Ted regarding $50 contribution to Floating Bear from Herbert B. Lutz.
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Nov 6, APCS, 1 p.
  "Louis Ginsberg is Allen Ginsberg's father!"
- L.J. to D.D. 1961 Nov 14, APCS, 1 p.
  Adds name and address to list.
- L.J. To D.D. 1961 Dec 18, APC, 1 p.
- L.J. to D.D. 1962 Jan 10, APCS, 1 p.
  Directs Kerouac's copies of Floating Bear to care of an Orlando, Florida address.
- L.D. to D.D. 1962 Jan 28, ALS, 1 p. w/env.
  Suggests that poems by (Arthur?) Freeman, Marshall, (Gary) Snyder, (Daisy) Aldan be published in Bear.
- L.J. to D.D. 1962 May 1, TLS, 1 p. w/env.
  Asks for three or four pieces of Di Prima's recent prose for an anthology of avant-garde American fiction. Discusses payment and specifications.
- L.J. to D.D. 1962 May 4, APCS, 1 p.
  Informs her of times and address for an open performance of "Toilet."
- L.J. to D.D. 1963 Mar 19, TLS, 1 p. w/env.
  Expresses satisfaction with the new Bear and hopes that it will continue. Says he can't be listed as an editor anymore, suggests Joel (Oppenheimer) or Frank (O'Hara) "could handle it from this end," meaning New York. Asks for certain back issues. Describes self as "hungover," mentions Edward Denby's 60th birthday party. "I teach the one class at The new school. Against everything anybody wants to feel. Gesture. Necessity, a vague social category, I must imagine. Not even corrupt." Says he saw her play at the Judson, briefly discusses Jimmy's performance in it. Asks that none of his poems on file at Bear be published, as "They haven't worn well at all."
- L.J. to D.D. 1963 May 17, ALS, 1 p. w/env.
  Has "just gotten out of Bellevue, where I had been locked up for two weeks getting out from under Hepatitis (of the dirty needle variety)." Is recovering at his parents' house. Asks if she has found a publisher for the New Handbook, says Larry W. (Wallrich) and he are publishing "quite a few titles this Fall" and would be interested in her work or in "any other book you felt shd [sic] see the light." Gives press run and financial information, mailing instructions.
- L.J. to D.D. May 30, APCS, 1 p.
  Asks if (Jean) Genet's "Man Condemned to Death" should be published as a Bear, discusses other possibilities for use of the piece. Has found three old poems in his files.
- L.J. to D.D. n.d., APC, 1 p.
  Name and address of Dave Ossman, a Bear contributor.
- L.J. to D.D. n.d., TLS, 1 p. w/env.
  Says he liked "The Beach," especially the middle sections. Says authors in "4 Young Lady Poets" will tentatively be Di Prima, Barbara Guest, Barbara Moraff, and Rochelle Owens or Daisy Aldan. Says he would like to include "the jungle, the beach, & c." Mentions Alfred (Leslie), Paul (Blackburn), Larry Wallrich, and a "violent argument" between (Howard) Nemerov and "Ab" or "AB" (A.B. Spellman?) at Bennington. Briefly describes a reading by Die Neue Akademie with Joel (Oppenheimer), Max (Finstein), Gil (Gilbert Sorrentino), Joe Early, and Tony Weinberger for their new magazine "Al Que Quiere."